Intro 00:00:01,989 --&gt;
This is a video for anyone who already knows
00:00:06,060 3 трюк,
what eigenvalues and eigenvectors are, and
who might enjoy a quick way to compute them
але, якщо
in the case of 2x2 matrices. If you’re unfamiliar
with eigenvalues, take a look at this video
можливо, я хотів
which introduces them.
би, щоб
You can skip ahead if you just want to see
ви знову його
відкрили для себе,
let’s lay down a little background.
тому 00:00:23,349
As a quick reminder, if the effect of a linear
transformation on a given vector is to scale
--&gt; 00:00:28,550 8
it by some constant, we call it an "eigenvector"
of the transformation, and we call the relevant
часто позначається
scaling factor the corresponding "eigenvalue,"
літерою лямбда. Коли
ви записуєте це у
a little bit, what you see is that if the
вигляді рівняння та
number lambda is an eigenvalue of a matrix
A, then the matrix (A minus lambda times the
переставляєте 00:00:47,320 --&gt; 00:00:53,190
identity) must send some nonzero vector, namely
the corresponding eigenvector, to the zero
12 цієї модифікованої матриці
vector, which in turn means the determinant
має бути 0.
00:01:09,960 --&gt;
to say, but again, I’m assuming all of this
00:01:12,829
is review for anyone watching.
00:01:12,829 --&gt;
So, the usual way to compute eigenvalues,
how I used to do it, and how I believe most
00:01:17,939
students are taught to carry it out, is to
subtract the unknown value lambda off the
17 дорівнює
diagonals and then solve for when the determinant
0.
Для цього завжди
expand out and simplify to get a clean quadratic
потрібно кілька кроків
polynomial, what's known as the “characteristic
polynomial” of the matrix. The eigenvalues
до 00:01:32,630 --&gt;
are the roots of this polynomial. So to find
them you have to apply the quadratic formula,
00:01:38,069 ще 21
which itself typically requires one or two
кроку спрощення.
Чесно кажучи, процес не страшний. Але
at least for 2x2 matrices, there’s a much
00:01:52,710 --&gt;
more direct way to get at this answer. And
if you want to rediscover this trick, there
00:01:57,049 25 сума
are only three relevant facts you need to
know, each of which is worth knowing in its
цих двох
own right and can help you with other problem-solving.
діагональних елементів
Number 1: The trace of a matrix, which is
дорівнює сумі власних
значень. Або
way to phrase it, more useful for our purposes,
інше 00:02:14,700 --&gt;
is that the mean of the two eigenvalues is
the same as the mean of these two diagonal
00:02:18,959 30
entries.
31 має сенс,
Number 2: The determinant of a matrix, our
usual ad-bc formula, is equal to the product
якщо ви розумієте,
of the two eigenvalues. And this should kind
що власні
значення описують, наскільки
in a particular direction and that the determinant
оператор розтягує простір
describes how much an operator scales areas
(or volumes) as a whole.
00:02:37,720 --&gt;
Now before getting to the third fact, notice
how you can essentially read these first two
00:02:42,189 35 вниз.
values out of the matrix without really writing
Візьмемо цю матрицю як приклад.
Відразу ви можете
the eigenvalues is the same as the mean of
знати, що
8 and 6, which is 7. Likewise, most linear
algebra students are pretty well-practiced
середнє 00:02:55,970 --&gt;
at finding the determinant, which in this
case works out to be 48 - 8 So right away
00:03:02,420 39
you know that the product of our two eigenvalues
дорівнює 40.
Тепер знайдіть хвилинку, щоб
what will be our third relevant fact, which
побачити, як ви можете
is how to recover two numbers when you know
their mean and you know their product.
вивести 00:03:17,079 --&gt; 00:03:21,860
Here, let's focus on this example. You know
the two values are evenly spaced around 7,
43, назвемо це чимось
so they look like 7 plus or minus something;
&quot;d&quot; для відстані.
Ви також знаєте, що
numbers is 40. Now to find d, notice that
добуток цих двох
this product expands really nicely, it works
out as a difference of squares. So from there,
00:03:40,239 --&gt; 00:03:45,480 47
you can directly find d: d^2 is 7^2 - 40,
or 9, which means d itself is 3.
конкретних прикладів виходить
In other words, the two values for this very
4 і 10.
Але нашою метою є
want to think this through each time, so let’s
швидкий трюк, і ви
wrap up what we just did in a general formula.
For any mean, m and product, p, the distance
не 00:04:06,239 --&gt; 00:04:12,610
squared is always going to be m^2 - p. This
gives the third key fact, which is that when
51 ви можете записати
two numbers have a mean m and a product p,
ці два числа як
m ± sqrt(m^2 -
p). Це досить швидко
if you ever forget it, and it’s essentially
для повторного виведення на
just a rephrasing of the difference of squares
formula. But even still it’s a fact worth
льоту 00:04:34,490 --&gt; 00:04:39,360
memorizing so that you have it at the tip
of your fingers.
56 написав нам короткий
In fact, my friend Tim from the channel acapellascience
джингл, щоб зробити його
трохи більш запам&#39;ятовуваним.
m плюс-мінус squaaaa є
minus p (ping!)
корінь з мене
Let me show you how this works, say for the
matrix [[3,1], [4,1]]. You start by bringing
в квадраті 00:04:53,880
to mind the formula, maybe stating it all
in your head. But when you write it down,
--&gt; 00:04:59,069 61 p.
you fill in the appropriate values of m and
Тож у цьому
прикладі середнє власних значень таке
of 3 and 1, which is 2. So the thing you start
ж, як і середнє.
writing is 2 ± sqrt(2^2 - …). Then the
product of the eigenvalues is the determinant,
00:05:19,030 --&gt; 00:05:26,780 65
which in this example is 3*1 - 1*4, or -1.
So that’s the final thing you fill in. This
може розпізнати, що це
means the eigenvalues are 2±sqrt(5). You
та сама матриця, яку
я використовував на початку,
much more directly we can get at the answer.
але зауважте, як 00:
Here, try another one. This time the mean
of the eigenvalues is the same as the mean
05:47,370 --&gt; 00:05:52,190 69 це
of 2 and 8, which is 5. So again, you start
writing out the formula but this time writing
2*8 - 7*1 або
5 in place of m [song]. And then the determinant
9. Тож у цьому
прикладі власні значення
simplifies even further as 9 and 1.
виглядають як 5 ±
You see what I mean about how you can basically
just start writing down the eigenvalues while
sqrt(16), що 00:06:19,590
staring at the matrix? It’s typically just
the tiniest bit of simplifying at the end.
--&gt; 00:06:23,800 73 дуже
Honestly, I’ve found myself using this trick
багато, коли я роблю
короткі замітки, пов’язані
as examples. I’ve been working on a video
з лінійною алгеброю, і
about matrix exponents, where eigenvalues
pop up a lot, and I realized it’s just very
хочу використовувати маленькі
handy if students can read off the eigenvalues
from small examples without losing the main
матриці 00:06:37,039 --&gt; 00:06:41,800
line of thought by getting bogged down in
77 інший розрахунок.
Як ще один цікавий
set of three different matrices, which come
приклад, подивіться на
up a lot in quantum mechanics, they're known
as the Pauli spin matrices. If you know quantum
цю 00:06:54,190 --&gt; 00:06:59,419
mechanics, you’ll know that the eigenvalues
of matrices are highly relevant to the physics
81 механіку, нехай
they describe, and if you don’t know quantum
це буде лише коротке
уявлення про те,
to real applications.
наскільки ці обчислення насправді
The mean of the diagonal in all three cases
is 0, so the mean of the eigenvalues in all
актуальні 00:07:12,639 --&gt;
cases is 0, which makes our formula look especially
simple.
00: 07:19,990 85 детермінанти
What about the products of the eigenvalues,
цих матриць? Для першого
це 0 - 1 або -1. Другі
also looks like 0 - 1, but it takes a moment
00:07:36,430 --&gt; 00:07:42,310 89
more to see because of the complex numbers.
And the final one looks like -1 - 0. So in
знають, що вони
all cases, the eigenvalues simplify to be
±1. Although in this case, you really don’t
рівномірно розподілені навколо
need the formula to find two values if you
0, а їхній
добуток дорівнює -1.
Якщо вам цікаво, у
mechanics, these matrices describe observations
контексті квантової 00:07:59,759 --&gt;
you might make about a particle's spin in
the x, y or z directions. The fact that their
00:08:04,470 94 чи зовсім
eigenvalues are ±1 corresponds with the idea
that the values for the spin that you would
в іншому, на
observe would be either entirely in one direction
відміну від чогось постійного
між ними. Можливо,
wonder how exactly this works, or why you
ви б 00:08:20,680 --&gt;
would use 2x2 matrices that have complex numbers
to describe spin in three dimensions. And
00:08:26,259 98, тому
those would be fair questions, just outside
the scope of what I want to talk about here.
що я хотів якийсь
You know it’s funny, I wrote this section
випадок, де у
вас є матриці 2x2,
or homework problems, ones where they actually
які не є
come up in practice, and quantum mechanics
is great for that. But the thing is after
просто іграшковими прикладами 00:08:38,970
I made it I realized that the whole example
kind of undercuts the point I’m trying to
--&gt; 00:08:43,880 102
make. For these specific matrices, when you
використовуйте традиційний метод, метод
із характеристичними поліномами,
it might actually faster. I mean, take a look
по суті, такий же
a the first one: The relevant determinant
directly gives you a characteristic polynomial
швидкий; 00:08:58,700 --&gt;
of lambda^2 - 1, and clearly, that has roots
of plus and minus 1. Same answer when you
00:09:03,390 106 для останньої
do the second matrix, lambda^2 - 1. And as
матриці, забудьте про
будь-які обчислення, традиційні чи
already a diagonal matrix, so those diagonal
інші, це 00:09:20,940
entries are the eigenvalues!
--&gt; 00:09:23,510 00:09:23,510 --
However, the example is not totally lost to
our cause. Where you will actually feel the
&gt; 00:09:28,850 111
speed up is in the more general case where
you take a linear combination of these three
один, плюс b, помножене
matrices and then try to compute the eigenvalues.
на друге, плюс
You might write this as a times the first
c, помножене на третє.
У квантовій механіці
describe spin observations in a general direction
це 00:09:47,360 --&gt;
of a vector with coordinates [a, b, c]. More
specifically, you should assume this vector
00:09:53,240 116 все
is normalized, meaning a^2 + b^2 + c^2 = 1.
When you look at this new matrix, it’s immediate
ще дорівнює нулю, і
to see that the mean of the eigenvalues is
ви також можете
насолоджуватися короткою паузою,
of those eigenvalues is still -1, and then
щоб переконатися, що
from there concluding what the eigenvalues
must be. And this time, the characteristic
добуток 00:10:13,560 --&gt;
polynomial approach would be by comparison
a lot more cumbersome, definitely harder to
00:10:10: 18,710 120 принципово
do in your head.
не відрізняється від
To be clear, using the mean-product formula
знаходження коренів характеристичного
многочлена; Я 00:10:33,110
mean, it can't be, they're solving the same
--&gt; 00:10:37,160 125
problem. One way to think about this, actually,
is that the mean-product formula is a nice
коренів квадратичного числа з
way to solve quadratic in general (and some
viewers of the channel may recognize this).
урахуванням його коефіцієнтів,
This about it: When you’re trying to find
це інша ситуація,
коли ви знаєте
sum of two values, and you also know their
00:10:50,950 --&gt; 00:10:54,820
product, but you’re trying to recover the
original two values.
129 лінійний коефіцієнт, який
Specifically, if the polynomial is normalized
so that this leading coefficient is 1, then
є -1 помножити
the mean of the roots will be -½ times this
на суму цих
коренів. Для прикладу
screen that makes the mean 5. And the product
00:11:12,820 --&gt;
of the roots is even easier, it’s just the
constant term no adjustments needed. So from
00:11:17,610 133
there, you would apply the mean product formula
and that gives you the roots.
полегшеної версії
On the one hand, you could think of this as
традиційної квадратичної формули.
Але справжня
is that it's fewer symbols to memorize, it's
перевага 00:11:34,200 --&gt;
that each one of them carries more meaning
with it.
00:11:37,370 137 вам
The whole point of this eigenvalue trick is
that because you can read out the mean and
не потрібно проходити
product directly from looking at the matrix,
проміжний крок встановлення
характеристичного полінома.
You can jump straight to writing down the
00:11:49,930 --&gt; 00:11:54,339 141
roots without ever explicitly thinking about
what the polynomial looks like. But to do
для дуже конкретної
that we need a version of the quadratic formula
where the terms carry some kind of meaning.
аудиторії, але я
I realize that this is a very specific trick,
хотів би це
знати в коледжі,
to know any students who might benefit from
тому, якщо ви трапитеся
this, consider sharing it with them.
00:12:08,240 --&gt; 00:12:10,330
The hope is that it’s not just one more
thing to memorize, but that the framing reinforces
00:12 00:12:10,330 --&gt;
some other nice facts worth knowing, like
how the trace and determinant relate to eigenvalues.
00:12:15,140 146 знайдіть
If you want to prove those facts, by the way,
хвилинку, щоб розгорнути
характерний поліном для загальної
hard about the meaning of each of these coefficients.
матриці, і подумайте
Many thanks to Tim, for ensuring that this
mean-product formula will stay stuck in all
00:12:32,449 --&gt; 00:12:36,420
of our heads for at least a few months. If
you don’t know about acapellascience, please
150 зокрема, це
do check it out. "The Molecular Shape of You",
одна з найбільших
речей в інтернеті.